<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-06T20:41:55+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Project Faial - Building a basic drone</title><subtitle>Follow along as we build our first drone from scratch.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Building blocks of a drone</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/preparing/for/build/2021/05/06/Makeup-of-drone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building blocks of a drone" /><published>2021-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/preparing/for/build/2021/05/06/Makeup-of-drone</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/preparing/for/build/2021/05/06/Makeup-of-drone.html">&lt;p&gt;The first thing we did in our journey to build a drone was to read up on what it would require to build a drone. These articles are mentioned in a &lt;a href=&quot;/starting/blog/2021/04/13/Planning.html&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;. As I said in the &lt;a href=&quot;/starting/blog/2021/04/18/How-does-a-drone-work.html&quot;&gt;last blog post&lt;/a&gt;, a drone works by fulfilling three things: having a flight mechanism, a source of power, and a brain. Four if you include the body/frame. I’ll go over these in detail here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things to keep in mind when making an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) aka drone:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-its-size-and-the-material-for-the-frame&quot;&gt;1. It’s size and the material for the frame&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bigger obviously means more pricy. Certain materials obviously will be more costly. &lt;strong&gt;Carbon fiber&lt;/strong&gt; is a popular option due to it’s light weight durability. Carbon fiber does come with a downside that it blocks radio frequency signals. Which can be accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2--getting-it-up-in-the-air&quot;&gt;2.  Getting it up in the air.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight mechanism: motors, propellers, and controlling the speed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAV’s differ depending on the number of &lt;strong&gt;rotors&lt;/strong&gt; (the part that spins). Quadcopter is the most popular with 4 rotors, but there are also tricopters (3 rotors) , hexacopters (6 rotors), and octocopers (8 rotors). More rotors naturally leads to more flight power, more storage capacity, and more redundancy. This comes at a higher price tag, and also requires a bigger battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motors&lt;/strong&gt; converts electrical energy to mechanical energy that leads to spin. It does this by basically playing around with differences in magnetic fields. You might remember that opposite charges attract, and same charges repel. The two kinds of motors, brushed and brushless, exploit these magnetic properties in different ways to generate spin. The difference between the two can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C1-klL3B9LU&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;. In short brushed motors are cheaper &amp;amp; simpler but less efficient and not durable. Brushless are more expensive but more efficient and are therefore usually recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Propellers are the ‘wings’ which attach to the rotors to achieve altitude. These spin either clockwise or counterclockwise and come in different kinds of materials ( such as plastic) and sizes. Larger blades change velocity slower or, while smaller blades can easily change direction or speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-powering-it-up&quot;&gt;3. Powering it up&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything needs energy, a UAV is no exception. As mentioned before, bigger drones require more energy, which means a bigger battery. It was surprising to me to find out that most drones last around than ten minutes in the air. Naturally, flight time is dependent on how much battery is available!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that the voltage of the battery need to match that of the rotors, since rotors will be needing to convert this energy to mechanical spin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-drone-control&quot;&gt;4. Drone control&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least is the brain. The brain of a UAV is the flight controller. The flight controller does what it’s name says: controls the flight. It tells the rotors how fast to spin and in which direction. It reads in sensory data from the surroundings &amp;amp; the drone (air pressure, angular position, acceleration). And it’s where all the fun autonomous flight possibilities lie.  You can either buy a prepackaged flight controller or you can make your own from an arduino or rasberry pi!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;add-ons&quot;&gt;Add ons&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of other additional things you can add to your flight experience. A camera, goggles, a remote control, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>christine</name></author><category term="preparing" /><category term="for" /><category term="build" /><summary type="html">The first thing we did in our journey to build a drone was to read up on what it would require to build a drone. These articles are mentioned in a previous blog post. As I said in the last blog post, a drone works by fulfilling three things: having a flight mechanism, a source of power, and a brain. Four if you include the body/frame. I’ll go over these in detail here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How does a drone work?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/starting/blog/2021/04/18/How-does-a-drone-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does a drone work?" /><published>2021-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/starting/blog/2021/04/18/How-does-a-drone-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/starting/blog/2021/04/18/How-does-a-drone-work.html">&lt;p&gt;After watching beautiful footage from drone videos, observing their gain in popularity over the years, and possibly even seeing one in real life you come up with the best idea ever - you’re gonna build a drone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just one problem. You’ve never actually built a drone before. So, umm… actually how do those things get up in the air?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the question I kept coming back to. I really wanted to wrap my head around the concept of flight. And how a drone actually functions. If you’ve ever wondered this, I hope this post can help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;basics-for-flight&quot;&gt;Basics for flight&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I’m concerned, in order for any aerial vehicle to function, it needs to satisfy 3 basic requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flight mechanism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Energy to power itself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A brain to control everything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Well, 4 things if you include a body to house everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;flight-mechanism&quot;&gt;Flight mechanism&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many methods to propel a device off the ground. A bird has wings, a plane also has wings of sorts. When we jump we use energy from our legs to project us up. The method a drone flies is by pushing air downwards. Imagine a small fan facing downwards. Now imagine multiple of them connected by a piece of cardboard. That’s basically a drone. Spinning blades push the air in a certain direction. The ‘fans’ of a drone are called rotors, and they work basically the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;energy&quot;&gt;Energy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well if you have a fan, how do you get it to spin on it’s own? Just like you plug in your fan, the aerial vehicle needs a power source. It would be inconvenient for the vehicle to be wired all the time, so naturally a battery is used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;brain&quot;&gt;Brain&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great! It has a way to fly and energy to make it fly…But how does it know what to do or where to go? It needs a central area that is in charge of moving the rotors to control flight, and doing any other tasks that you want a drone to do. This is the brain’s of the vehicle and it’s called the flight controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it. A drone! Of course there’s other things that go into making a drone, but these are the 3 central parts. Everything else revolves around enhancing these parts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>christine</name></author><category term="starting" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">After watching beautiful footage from drone videos, observing their gain in popularity over the years, and possibly even seeing one in real life you come up with the best idea ever - you’re gonna build a drone!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting started</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/starting/blog/2021/04/13/Planning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting started" /><published>2021-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/starting/blog/2021/04/13/Planning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/starting/blog/2021/04/13/Planning.html">&lt;p&gt;Neither of us knew much about electronics, so our first step was to read as much as possible about drones. We came across a great deal of blogs, acronyms, and formats to create a drone, one subtype of unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV). Here are a subset of things we considered during our first steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-many-drones&quot;&gt;How many drones?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fiddled with the idea of simultaneously working on two drones, but decided perhaps it’s best to focus on one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-kind-of-drone&quot;&gt;What kind of drone?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ultimately decided on a quadcopter (a UAV with four rotors), as it seemed to be the most standard model&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-manage-our-project&quot;&gt;How to manage our project?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We settled on using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.todoist.com/&quot;&gt;todoist&lt;/a&gt; to track responsibilities and share tasks. Todoist is basically as it’s name sounds. An app that enables simple to do lists in a clean fashion. So far it has worked well for us. We used a google drive folder to share documents and links&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;which-sites-were-the-most-helpful&quot;&gt;Which sites were the most helpful?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most helpful source for us was this &lt;a href=&quot;http://beginnerflyer.com/build-a-drone/&quot;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; that went over everything on how to build a drone from scratch. This was basically our guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K05UwsiqZ_E&quot;&gt;Drone parts 101&lt;/a&gt; This youtube video gave me a pretty good overview of the different parts of the drone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this information in the next blog post, I’ll answer the biggest question that was on my mind during these early days….how the heck does a drone work?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="starting" /><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Neither of us knew much about electronics, so our first step was to read as much as possible about drones. We came across a great deal of blogs, acronyms, and formats to create a drone, one subtype of unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV). Here are a subset of things we considered during our first steps.</summary></entry></feed>